The agentic loop has no natural stopping condition by design.
Each iteration costs tokens.
Input tokens for the full context you are resending every turn plus output tokens for
the reply.
On a 200,000 token context, one loop iteration can cost 30 cents, 50 iterations, 15 dollars.
And a model that's stuck chasing a bug it can't reproduce or oscillating between two
tool calls will happily loop until you stop it or your credit goes out.
The fix has two parts.
Hard iteration limits.
Set a max iteration's budget before the agent starts.
Not a suggestion.
A kill switch.
Claude code's default is around 200.
Production systems are often tighter, 10 to 20 for focused tasks.
Stall detection.
If the last three tool calls are identical you are in a loop.
Surface it.
Stop the agent.
Ask the human what to do next.
Don't let the model retry its way to the bankruptcy.
But iterations are just one meter.
Runaway cost runs on three.
Steps, tokens and wall clock time.
So budget all the three.
A token card.
A hard time out.
Not only a loop limit.
Very serious framework shifts these now.
Langraff halts at 25 steps by default.
Autogen has a separate token and time out cutoffs.
The OpenAI agent's SDK cap turns and throws the moment you blow past it.
And the smartest stop isn't a counter at all.
It's progress.
If the tests are still read and the file is unchanged, the agent isn't working.
It's failing.
Stop on no progress even at iteration three.
One number to hold onto.
Cost scales with context length times iterations.
A bloated context makes runaway loops catastrophically expensive.