Here is the one that surprises people.
A longer conversation makes the model dumber.
The model re-reads the entire context every single turn.
Early in a task, the context is tight.
System prompt, tools, the goal.
But tool results pile up fast.
A grep that returned 800 lines.
A file read that was only partially relevant.
A failed attempt that's now just noise.
By turn 30, the model is wading through thousands of tokens
of junk to find the three lines that actually matter.
This is context rot.
And it causes real regressions.
The model starts losing the thread,
contradicting its earlier decisions,
forgetting things it knew 10 turns ago.
The fix is context engineering.
You don't dump everything into the prompt.
You curate it.
Summaries instead of raw tool output.
Truncated file reads with the relevant section highlighted.
Compaction that preserves decisions, not transcripts.
Curation has a deeper move than trimming.
Get the junk out of the window entirely.
Offload to a subagent.
Let a helper burn 30,000 tokens reading
and hand back a 2,000 token summary.
The noise never touches the main thread.
Write to a memory file.
Notes on disk, the agent re-reads.
So state outlives the window.
And mind the middle.
Models reliably lose what's buried
in the middle of a long context.
It's a U-shaped curve, sharp at the start and end,
weak in between, and a bigger window doesn't fix it.
Put what matters at the edges.
Think of the harness as the model's working memory.
Treat it like RAM, not a hard drive.
Keep only what the model needs right now.
Everything else is noise.
And noise costs you IQ points per turn.