More tools feels like more power, it's not.
When you hand a model 50 tools, you have given it a decision problem on every turn.
Which tool fits here, read file or get file contents, search code base or grep files.
The names blur, the descriptions overlap and the model makes bad picks or hedges, calling
two tools where one would do.
Tools Prawl also inflates the context directly.
Every tool definition, name, description, typed parameters, costs tokens before the
model writes a single character.
50 tools can burn 8000 tokens on tool schemas alone.
The fix?
Fewer, sharper tools.
Each tool should do one thing with an unmistakable name.
If two tools are overlapping descriptions, merge them or delete them.
Cloud Code ships around 15 core tools, not as a limitation, but as a deliberate design
choice.
The model picks faster and picks better when the menu is short.
A good rule of thumb, if you can't describe what a tool does in 5 words, it's too vague
to be useful.
But there is a sharper move than trimming the list by hand.
Low tools on demand.
Keep the big catalog, just expose the 3 to 5 relevant tools each turn, in Anthropics own
testing that took 58 tools.
55,000 tokens before you type a word, down to about 3,000 and lifted tool selection accuracy
from 49 to 74%.
Same model, shorter menu.
One level further with Code Mode.
Let the model write code that calls the tools and filters the results before they ever hit
the context.
Anthropic measured a 37% token cut on complex tasks that fixes tool sprawl and context rot
in one stroke.