Here is a problem that sounds simple but turns out to be one of the harder things in AI right
now.
You point an agent at your whole code base or your company's entire knowledge base.
That's millions of tokens far more than fits in this context window.
Then you ask one question and the answer lives in maybe three sentences buried somewhere
in all of that.
So how does the agent find those three sentences?
If it dumps everything in, it slows down, it costs more, and it actually gets less accurate
which we covered last time.
The real skill is the opposite.
Pulling in only the right context exactly when it's needed, that's retrieval.
And it's changed a lot recently.
Let's walk through it.