You already know the basic loop, embed your docs,
embed the query, grab the nearest chunks.
We will skip that because what actually decides
whether retrieval works happens earlier at indexing time
and most setups get it wrong.
Start with chunking.
The moment you split a document up,
each chunk loses the context around it.
A line like the fee is $50 gets stored as a naked blob
with no record that it lived under Section 4 refunds.
Retrieve it later and the model has no idea
what it's looking at.
Chunks too big and you drag in noise.
Too small and you lose the meaning.
This one decision sets a ceiling
on how good your system can get.
There's a useful upgrade here.
Anthropic calls it contextual retrieval.
Before you embed a chunk, a cheap model writes a short note
on where it sits in the document and prepends it.
So the fee is $50 becomes in the refund policy,
the fee is $50.
Same chunk, but now it carries its context.
In an anthropic own testing, that single change
to the embedding's cut field retrievals by about a third
before you have even touched the search.
Fix the index and everything downstream gets easier.