With a solid index, the next question is the search itself.
And there is a result here worth knowing.
Semantic search is good at understanding what you mean.
Ask how do I reset my password and it finds a doc titled account recovery steps with no
matching words at all.
That's powerful.
But it has a blind spot, exact terms, error codes, product IDs, a function name.
The meaning matching blurs those out and on some 2026 benchmarks, plain keyword search
actually beat vector search outright.
So the better systems use both.
That's hybrid search, run keyword and semantic together and merge the rankings.
One catches the exact terms, the other catches the meaning.
Then there is one more layer, re-ranking.
Hybrid pulls a wide set, say 50 candidates.
A second smarter model rereads those 50 and resorts them.
So the best three rise to the top, cast a wide net quickly, then let a specialist pick
the winners.
Stack all of it, contextual embeddings, hybrid search and a re-rangle and in anthropic's
own testing, failed retrievals drop by about two thirds.
Same documents, same model, it just finds the right context far more often.
That's the modern retrieval stack.