Now to the part that's genuinely changing right now.
In classic RAG, retrieval happens once before the model even starts thinking.
Agentic retrieval asks a different question.
What if the model drove the search itself?
It's essentially the agent loop pointed at search.
Here is what changes.
The agent takes your question and reformulates it into a better query.
If it's complex, it breaks it into sub-questions and searches each one.
Then the key part, it looks at what came back and judges it.
Do I have enough?
No, the answer references something I haven't looked up yet.
So it searches again and keeps going until it has what it needs.
Instead of one blind grab, you get a small research loop.
Ask something that takes three hops to answer and classic RAG tends to fall apart.
While an agentic retrieval chains the hops and gets there.
This isn't free though.
It costs roughly three to ten times the tokens of classic RAG.
So use it where the question is genuinely hard not to look up a simple fact.