It also doesn't have to happen up front.
The agent can retrieve mid-task the moment it hits something it doesn't know.
Take a coding agent, it's editing a file, hits a function it doesn't recognize, and
right there in the loop it runs a search, grabs just that definition and moves on.
Retrieval becomes a tool the agent calls whenever it has a gap, just in time rather than just
in case.
And it's not only documents, the same machinery works on memory, past conversations, decisions,
notes about the user.
When something's relevant, the agent searches its own memory and pulls back the one item
that matters out of thousands.
Find the needle, leave the haystack.